This program is brought to you by
Stanford University. Please visit us at
stanford.edu.
All right, so we want to talk a little
bit about the laws of nature and the
form of the laws of nature take.
Now,
um
let me give you an example of a possible
law of nature,
which is not a law of nature,
but uh discuss what's wrong with it.
So, here's a law of nature.
Particles collide.
Here's my axes,
X and Y,
fixed and permanent on the blackboard or
fixed and permanent in space.
And the rule is particles will collide
and go off in weird directions
whenever
their X coordinate is the same.
Whenever the two particles, whenever
their X coordinates become the same,
they suddenly turn around or go off in
some other direction.
So, for example,
if this particle is moving this way and
this one is this way,
when they get to the same value of X,
the rule is something happens. We
needn't specify precisely what happens.
Maybe they get turned around or maybe
they go off in some other direction.
If they're moving
like
these two other particles,
they're moving in some other direction,
not horizontally, but they're moving
this way, that one's moving this way,
and this one's moving this way,
again, the rule is whenever their X
coordinates become the same,
they collide and go off and do something
else.
Well, that's a possible law of nature.
It could it could it could have been
like that.
There's nothing mathematically
inconsistent with it,
but it just doesn't seem right. It seems
to violate something that's deeply
ingrained
uh both in physics and the laws of
physics and in our own intuition.
What is it?
What's the rule that's being violated?
What? Homogeneity.
Not homogeneity. No. It's Okay, good.
It's not homogeneity. Homogeneity says
that you can translate things
and they'll stay the same, that the laws
of nature are independent
of where you put the center of your
coordinates.
And this is independent of where you put
your
your the center of your coordinates.
specify the X. Hm? Cuz you didn't
specify the X. Yes, I didn't specify the
X. I just told you whenever X becomes
equal,
they collide.
So, we could say it this way. If we have
two particles
and they have coordinates, one called X1
and the this is not the component of the
coordinate. This is just labels which
particle we're talking about. When X1
minus X of two
become equal to zero, they collide.
That's our rule. When the difference
between the two X's are equal to zero,
they collide. Well, that doesn't specify
what particular value of X. It could be
X way out here. It could be X way over
there. They'll collide. If we lift
everything up vertically, they'll
collide. If we lift everything down
vertically,
so in fact, it doesn't violate
homogeneity of space. Space is
everywhere is the same in this rule.
Yeah.
That means you can always find some
coordinate where you can make them
collide any how you want.
No, but the rule here is they they
always collide and if and only if their
X's are equal.
Right.
This violates the isotropy of space.
It violates the idea
that when you rotate coordinates, the
laws of physics stay the same. That the
laws of physics are the same and
independent of the orientation of your
axes. Not the place where you put your
origin, but the orientation of your
axes. So, for example, if I reoriented
my axes,
so that they look like
Well, I'm going to reorient them so that
um
this becomes the Y coordinate. Let's
see, the Y coordinate now is over here
and the X coordinate is over here. I'm
simply relabeling. It is a rotation of
my coordinates, a rotation by 90°.
Then exactly the same physics
will require us to say that particles
would collide when the Y's are equal.
Different law,
different form.
If we oriented the axes in some awkward
and arbitrary direction,
then the law would become much more
complicated. Some combination They would
they would only interact or they would
only collide when some combination of
the X's and Y's were equal.
So,
what would be violated here is the law
that says the law the laws of physics
are the same in every coordinate system,
independent
of the angles or independent of the
angle of the X axis.
However,
we do have to ensure
that the coordinates are perpendicular
to each other. There are things in the
rules of physics which require us to use
perpendicular coordinates to express the
law. We can express the laws of physics
in any coordinates we like,
but they take a special and simple form
in coordinates for which the axes are
perpendicular to each other.
Right?
But the rule that says that it doesn't
matter which way we orient our
coordinates. It doesn't matter if I look
at you this way or this way or this way
or this way, the laws of physics should
be the same.
Uh that's violated here.
Okay.
Let me give you an example of a law of
physics which is not violated, which
does not violate the rule that um
uh
that laws of physics should be the same.
Rotational invariant. This is called
rotational invariance. Invariance under
rotation of axes.
Let's require that particles only
interact if both the X coordinates of
the two particles and the Y coordinates
of the two particles
are equal
are equal.
In other words,
if X1 equals X2 and if Y1 equals Y2,
what does that say? That says that the
particles collide with each other.
Whatever it is they do, maybe they turn
around. That I'm not I'm not going to
specify exactly what they do,
but
the rule now would be they can only
collide
if they hit the same point.
In other words, if both the X coordinate
and the Y coordinates are equal, then
they collide. In fact, they don't even
have to be moving along the same line.
If a particle comes in along this axis
and a particle comes in along this axis
and they find themselves at exactly the
same point,
then they collide. Right?
That would be a law of nature that would
be the same no matter how we orient our
axes. If they collide when they come to
the same point, then it doesn't matter
whether we use this axis, whether we use
this axis.
And so, this law of physics
would
be one which was invariant under
rotations. Would be the same no matter
what orientation we chose for our axes.
I am not I For the moment, I'm just
ignoring time.
For the moment, yeah, yeah, of course we
do, but I was about to come to that.
Okay. What about Z coordinate?
If there if there's a Z coordinate, yes.
If there's a Z coordinate, yes.
Right. So, exactly so.
And
if space is three-dimensional,
if Z of one
is equal to Z of two. If and only if
these conditions are satisfied,
uh then two particles will collide. Come
to time in a minute.
All right, we can re-express this
in a single equation using vectors.
We think of the position of a particle
as a vector.
Let's call that position R.
I'll put a little arrow on top to
indicate a vector, but now I mean a
three-dimensional vector in ordinary
space. No time for the moment. We'll
come back to time in a minute.
All right? We can write this as one
equation.
We can write it that
the particle collides only
if R1 is equal to R2 or R1 minus R of
two
is equal to zero. And this equation
implies all components of R should be
equal to zero.
It's a vector equation. It's a vector
equation. It has three components.
And it's rotationally invariant.
Okay.
Here's a fact. If a vector is zero,
and this vector is zero. This is the
this is the rule.
Particles collide when a certain vector
is zero.
If a vector is zero, it's zero in every
coordinate system.
In other words, if the if all components
of a vector being zero means all of its
components are being are equal to zero.
If all of the components of a vector are
equal to zero, that's true in every
coordinate system.
If one or two components of the vector
is equal to zero and the other one is
not,
then that is not something which is true
in every coordinate system. For example,
here's a vector whose x component is
equal to zero.
Right?
In some other coordinate system, the x
component of that vector is not equal to
zero.
So, a law
or a rule that would say this or that
happens when a certain x component of a
vector is equal to zero, that law will
not in general be rotationally
invariant. On the other hand, if we have
a vector which is equal to zero, that
means that it has no length at all
or that it's just
a vector of zero length, just the
origin,
then
that vector is zero in every coordinate
system, no matter how we rotate it.
That's why we express laws of nature in
terms of vectors.
That's why we choose to express them in
And the advantage of a vector
description, vectors transform in a
certain way. They transform when you
rotate coordinates, the components of
vectors change, they transform,
but all vectors transform the same way
when you rotate. So, if a vector is
equal to zero in one frame, it's equal
to zero in another frame. If two vectors
are equal in one frame, they are equal
in any frame.
And that's why we express That is the
reason that we express physics in terms
of vectors
because we know that when we express it
properly in terms of vectors, then the
rules are independent of the orientation
of
of our axes.
Now, let's come to time. What about
time?
We could
Let's let the horizontal axis be x
again, but now let the vertical axis be
time.
x and t.
Now, again, I could have a rule which
says particles collide
when
uh
Well, let's see.
Particle collisions take place
only
when the time
of the two particles is the same. What
would that mean? That would mean that
it's possible for two particles to
collide.
This indicates a particle going forward
and then going backward. So, it's moving
along the x-axis, it's moving along
moving back along the x-axis.
It's possible for particles to collide
like that
when the two times are equal. It's
possible for them to collide at an at a
later time
as long as the two times are equal.
Collide means both of their velocities
simultaneously change.
Okay, that's what I mean by collide,
that their velocities simultaneously
change, but always at the same time.
Okay?
That's a perfectly good law of physics
in Newtonian physics.
And in fact, it is even a true law of
physics in Newtonian physics.
Uh
Well, it is a it is a true it's it's a
possible law of physics. Particles
collide only
um
their their velocities change
simultaneously if they change at all.
Okay?
It's not a possible law in the special
theory of relativity, and the reason is
because of the idea of simultaneity is
not invariant.
So, if I had a law of nature which said
the two particles collide in one
particular frame, in your frame, only
when the times are equal,
then in some other frame of reference,
this frame of reference here,
the times of collision would not be the
same, and we would come to the
conclusion that the relativity principle
was not correct, that the laws of
physics are not the same in all
reference frames. There's one particular
reference frame
in which particle collisions take place
uh
at equal times. In another frames of
reference, it's a more complicated story
in which some combination of x's and t's
have to be equal. All right, that's not
the way physics works. The way physics
works
is Lorentz invariant. Lorentz invariant
means, again, that the laws of physics
are the same in all reference frames
moving one with respect to the other.
What does that entail about simple
particle collisions, very simple
particle collisions? Well, for very
simple particle collision, the simplest
kind of particle collision, particles
collide, they don't produce any other
particles, not very much happens, they
just bang into each other and they go
off.
That implies that
collisions can only take place
when the two particles find themselves
at the same space-time point.
In other words, not only when their
times are equal,
but when their positions are also equal.
If two particles only collide when
they're at the same event, the same
point of space-time,
then
it doesn't matter which coordinates you
use, being at the same space-time point
is an invariant concept.
So, that's a good law of physics from
the point of view of relativity theory,
that particles collide
not just when they're at the same
position in space, but also only at the
same time.
Uh that also can be expressed in a kind
of vector notation.
If we represent
the location of a particle
or a location of a point
along a particle trajectory
by a four-vector,
the four-vector now has not only
components x, y, and z, but it also has
a component t,
then we would add in one more equation
here,
that the particles can only collide at
an event,
and that event has to have the same
location in space and in time.
Now, you can say very much the same
words about space-time that I just that
I said about space.
If a vector in space-time
has one or two or three components which
are equal,
sorry, which are equal to zero. If a
vector has space component equal to
zero, that doesn't mean it's zero. It
can have a time component. Here's a
vector which has a time component but no
space component.
If I have some law of physics that says
nothing more than something or other
happens when the space components of a
vector are equal to zero, that's not
Lorentz invariant. And the reason is
because in some other frame of
reference,
the x's of these two points are not the
same.
The x's of these two points are not the
same in some other frame of reference.
And so, uh saying that something special
happens when the x components or the y
components or the z components of a
vector are equal to zero, that can't be
Lorentz invariant. The only Lorentz
invariant statement that you can make
concerning a rule about a vector is that
all of its components have to be equal
to zero. If If If in some frame of
reference, if if the law of nature is
that some components equal zero, then it
had better be all of them.
Why?
Because
if you rotate or Lorentz transform your
coordinates,
you will find an inconsistency unless
you require all of the components to be
equal to zero. So, as I said, a law of
physics could be
that all four components of the location
of the of two events What are the two
events? The two events are the sudden
turning around of one particle
and the sudden turning around of another
particle. Those are both events.
This law of physics would tell us that
this event the two events could only
happen if they were at the same
space-time point. Okay?
So, we express laws of physics in terms
of four-vectors
or objects which transform
in a particular coherent way.
Four-vectors transform, the components
transform into each other. We've seen,
for example, that under Lorentz
transformations, x and t, for example,
get mixed up with each other.
But they get mixed up in with with each
other in such a way that if all the
components are equal to zero in one
frame, then they're all equal to zero in
another frame. All right. So, we express
laws of physics in terms of objects
which transform,
and we always require either we
translate we transpose everything to the
left-hand side and say that its
components
are four-vector, transform as a
four-vector,
and must be equal to zero. Or sometimes
we might express the uh the laws of
physics as an equation with a left-hand
side and a right-hand side.
x of two,
y of two, z of two,
t of two.
We express this particular form is
expressing a certain rule by saying that
two four vectors are equal to each
other. Not that some four vector is
equal to zero, but a certain four vector
associated with one event is equal to
the four vector associated with the
other event. So, sometimes we express
them by setting something to zero,
sometimes we express something by
expressing a left-hand side equals a
right-hand side,
but the equations only make sense
in this particular kind of case if
they're whole expressions for entire
four vectors, not just for pieces of the
four vector.
Four vectors are of course things which
transform under Lorentz transformations
the same way that X, Y, Z, and T do.
So, let's let's define a four vector.
It's an object with four components.
One for each direction of space and one
for time.
And it transforms. What does it mean to
transform? It means its value as
measured in different reference frames
transform so that if I know it in one
reference frame, I can give you the rule
for computing it in another reference
frame.
For example, position,
velocity, and so forth transform from
one Lorentz frame to another.
Position, we know how that transforms.
Let's take the case of first a Lorentz
transformation.
Here's X equals X minus VT.
Uh Y This is X prime equals X minus VT
over square root of 1 minus V squared.
Incidentally,
the notation I keep writing square root
of 1 minus V squared in the denominator
here.
There's a standard notation, gamma,
is equal to 1 over the square root of 1
minus V squared.
Gamma of V. Gamma of V. It saves
writing.
There's nothing deep about it. It's just
a way of rewriting so so another way to
write this
is that it's gamma
times X minus VT.
Okay, what else? Y prime
Say it again.
Yeah, yeah, yeah. C is equal to 1. If we
want to put C back into the formulas, we
put it down here.
All right.
C is equal to 1.
Y prime is equal to Y.
Z prime is equal to Z.
And T prime
is equal to T minus VX
divided by
root 1 minus V squared
or gamma times T minus VX.
This is the transformation properties of
coordinates of an event.
Okay.
Other transformation properties involve
rotations of space.
Let me write down the transformations
associated with rotations of space.
Rotations of space are given Here's an
example.
There are many many axes that you can
rotate about, but if I just rotate about
the Z axis,
vertically is the Z axis, I rotate my
coordinates. X and Y get mixed up with
each other.
Uh
Z does not get mixed into it, and
neither does time if all I do is rotate
my my coordinate axes.
Then the equations would look not not
totally dissimilar to this.
Well,
not so not totally similar either, but
they would look like this.
X prime is equal to X times cosine of an
angle
plus Y times a sine of an angle.
Let's put in here plus 0 times Z plus 0
times T just to remember
that's that Z and T are also part of the
game.
Y prime
is equal to minus
Y
No, minus X, sorry. Minus X cosine
theta. No, minus X sine theta.
Minus X sine theta
plus Y cosine theta
plus 0 Z plus 0 T.
Z prime is equal to Z.
I'm stacking things equal to Z. I'm
stacking things up
so that uh
X always appears in the same place, Y
always appears in the same place, Z
always appears in the same place. We
would write 0 X plus 0 Y
plus Z plus 0 T.
I'm being pedantic by putting in all
these zeros here.
And finally,
uh T prime
is equal to T
with all the others being zero.
And so forth.
This tells me how things transform under
a rotation about about the Z axis. This
tells me how they transform
under a Lorentz transformation.
They're similar kinds of equations. In
each case, they're linear equations of a
form of a particular form. A matrix is
involved.
If I wanted to write this in matrix
form, I think I wrote that last time in
matrix form. In each case,
they're linear equations which have the
form
X prime mu. Now, mu goes
1, 2, 3, and 0.
1, 2, 3, and 0. 1 means X, 2 means Y, 3
means Z,
and 0 means time.
They're of the form X prime
is equal to some matrix
mu nu
times X nu.
For example, let me write down the
matrix
governing the Lorentz transformation. In
that case, the matrix let's let's let's
make some notation.
The first column will stand for X, the
second column will stand for Y, the
third column for Z, and the fourth
column for T, or the zeroth column. And
same with rows. X, Y, Z I'm just
labeling now the entries.
Okay, what are the entries here? Well,
from here you can see that X prime is
equal to gamma X. So, there's a gamma
over here.
Uh there's a minus
V
gamma over here
and a 0 0.
That indicates
that Y and Z don't come into this
equation, but there's a gamma X and a
gamma VT with a minus sign.
And so on. Let's see, Y prime, that's
equal to 0 times X plus 1 times Y plus 0
times Z plus 0 times T.
Same with Z. 1
0. And T prime, that's equal that has a
minus V gamma here.
and gamma.
That's the matrix which governs the
simple Lorentz transformation here.
The matrix
which would govern a rotation of space
would also be a matrix with 4 by 4
structure, but here I can just read it
right off here. The corresponding matrix
for a rotation about the Z axis, a
rotation about the Z axis,
would look like
uh
cosine theta
sine theta
0 0
uh minus sine theta
cosine theta
0 0
0 0 1 0 0 0 0 1.
That would be the matrix which
represents a a rotation. Now, you can
combine these transformations together
in a wide variety of ways by mixing up
rotations and Lorentz transformations.
For example, if I wanted to do a Lorentz
transformation along some different
angle, let's say an angle in the XY
plane,
then first I would make a coordinate
transformation that turned the X axis
into the new X axis. I would use the
rotation matrix here
to find new coordinates along which the
new X axis is along the direction that I
want to do the Lorentz transformation.
Then after having done that,
I would do a second transformation,
which would be a Lorentz transformation,
um
between time and new X axis. That would
entail multiplying these two matrices
together, basically.
That's what that's what the matrix for
the full rotation would be is it would
be the product of the full Lorentz
transformation or the full combination
of
Lorentz transformation and rotation
would involve the product of these.
But really,
it's enough to know that physics is
invariant under rotations and know how
to write the rotation matrices, and
invariant under the Lorentz boosts along
This is called a Lorentz boost. Boost
means you speed up the velocity.
It's enough to know those two
forms here
and know that you mix them up in all
kinds of ways to
to
do more general Lorentz transformations,
more general transformations.
Well, you get different answers.
You get different answers.
Yep. If you first Lorentz transformation
transform, let me show you why. Imagine
you first Lorentz transform, okay? So,
that brings you to a new coordinate
frame in which this is the new space
axis here.
All right?
And then you do your rotation. Your
rotation is a rotation about this plane
here, not this plane.
So, it depends on the order. If you
first Lorentz transformed and then
rotated, you would be rotating about a
different surface. You'll be rotating a
different surface
than if you first rotated and then
Lorentz transformed. So, the the order
of action does matter.
But, it's enough to know
these two and how to combine them to to
know how to do any
transformation of the kind
that applies to vectors. All right. So,
the more general statement
is that there's a matrix of some sort.
The matrix has to satisfy some rules.
All right. But, basically the rules are
that it's various kinds of products of
these matrices.
And we just write it in a more in a
general form that the primed coordinates
are some matrix times unprimed
coordinates.
And for each specific situation where we
want to where we want to transform from
one coordinate system to another, we
have to know what the matrix is.
But, usually we can figure that out.
We can also write this in the form
a column vector X prime is equal to a
matrix. Now, let's just think of that as
a matrix now times a column vector X.
Just think of it as matrix
multiplication or
manipulation of indices. Remember, I I
want to remind you one thing.
When you have repeated four-dimensional
indices like this, particularly when one
of them is exhibited as an upper index
and one of them is exhibited as a lower
index, repeating the indices means sum
over the sum over the indices. It's the
same summation that you would do if you
multiplied the matrix
or let's put it X1 X
X1 X2
X3
X0.
All right? When you work out the
components of the product, you have to
sum gamma times X prime plus zero times
X I'm sorry, gamma times X1 plus zero
times X2 plus zero times X3 and so
forth. That's the same sum that's
implicit here in summing over the
repeated index.
All right. So, this is just a notational
device for writing out generally what a
Lorentz transformation does. It's a
linear operation like that.
That's a special case. This is a special
case of the transformation of vectors,
where the vector in this case happens to
be the space-time position of a point.
There are other four vectors.
There are other four vectors which are
interesting. For example, the four
vector associated with velocity.
We'll come back to it. The four vector
associated with proper velocity.
Remember what proper velocity is?
Proper velocity is not
dx by dx by dt,
but it's the X mu by d tau.
Tau is proper time. First of all, before
we even go ahead, even before we talk
about four vectors, we should talk about
scalars. Scalars are things which are
the same in every reference frame.
For example, if we're talking about um
only rotations, let's forget for the
moment Lorentz transformations, just
rotations. All right? The temperature at
this point right over here
is the same no matter which way we
orient our axes.
So, temperature is a thing which doesn't
transform under rotations in any case.
Temperature is a scalar. It's a scalar
quantity, which means it doesn't have
components. It's just one number
characterizing it.
And the temperature of a point in space
doesn't depend on what what axes are
used to to describe it.
How about the distance between two
points?
The distance between two points. Now,
I'm not thinking about space-time. I'm
thinking only about space. The distance
between two points, it doesn't matter
which way I turn my head. The distance
between them, the number of inches
between these two points, is the same no
matter which way I orient my axes.
So, distance is also a scalar quantity.
Components of vectors are not scalar
quantities. They change from one
reference frame to another. But, the
distance between two points is a scalar
quantity.
All right?
I might have a
not a law of nature so much, but a
simple claim.
I might tell you, for example, that the
distance between two points measured in
meters happens to be the same as the
temperature measured in Fahrenheit.
All right. It's a stupid thing, but it
might be. I mean, it might be. What is
the temperature in in Fahrenheit in
here? About 70°?
Yeah. All right. So, I can imagine two
points separated by 70 cm.
And then I would tell you, it just so
happens that the distance between my
fists
measured in centimeters happens to be
the same as the temperature in the room.
Does that depend on which axes I use?
No, because the distance between the
points doesn't depend on the axes. The
temperature doesn't depend on the axes.
They're both scalar quantities.
And so, the the statement that the
temperature equals the distance,
that's a rotationally invariant
statement. And if it's true in one
frame, it will be true in every frame.
In this case, it's a statement about
scalar quantities. I should have talked
about scalars even before I mentioned
vectors. Vectors are more complicated.
Uh for vectors, if a thing is true,
it better be true for all components of
the vector.
Thing is true in every frame of
reference.
All right. Now,
this is a four vector.
And the meaning of saying it's a four
vector is first of all, it has four
components.
But,
let's call it
Well, let's just
call it
the general four vector, not this
specific one, but the general four
vector. Let's call it for the moment A
mu.
This one is usually called U mu.
But, let's just generalize and think
about the general notion of a four
vector and let's call it A mu.
Its components
are equal to A1,
A2,
A3,
and A4.
Or A0, sorry.
The definition of a four vector, and it
does apply
to the four velocity or the proper
velocity.
The definition of a four vector is it's
a thing which transforms. Again,
transforms means that if you know it in
one frame, you can determine it in
another frame. The definition is that it
transforms exactly the same way
as X, as the components of X.
So, if I know A in one frame, in another
frame, in the primed frame,
the components A prime mu are equal to L
mu nu
times their values in the first frame.
Exactly the same as X. For example, the
four components of A, if I just did a
ordinary Lorentz transform or
transformation,
would vary in exactly the same way as X,
Y, Z, and T.
I won't bother writing it down.
The the transformation properties of a
four vector are the same
as X, Y, Z, and T.
That's the definition of a four vector.
If a four vector is zero
in one frame of reference,
if this is zero in one frame of
reference, it's obviously zero in every
frame of reference. If every component
is zero here, then every component will
be zero here.
If two vectors are equal in one frame of
reference, then they will be equal in
every frame of reference, assuming all
four components are equal.
So, that's the value of thinking in
terms of
four vectors.
The things which are true are true in
every frame of reference.
This makes them useful for describing
the laws of physics,
which are supposed to be true in every
frame of reference.
Now,
representing a vector
in this form here
is called the contravariant form of the
vector. There is another form for the
same vector,
which is called the covariant form or
the covariant components. It's really
imagined to be the same geometric object
just described in a different way. And
to describe it, we put the mu
downstairs. It's upstairs, downstairs.
And what it is is it's the same
collection of components, exactly the
same, except the space components, 1 and
3,
are changed in sign. A1 A2
A3
minus minus A0.
Why on earth would I want to do that?
Well, first before why I want to do it,
let me just describe it mathematically a
little bit differently.
Here's the mathematical connection
between the two.
A mu
is equal to a certain matrix. I'll write
down that matrix in a moment.
Uh
mu nu
times A nu.
Now, before we do anything else, let's
look at this equation
before I even say what it means.
It has the nice feature that
it's first of all summed over the new
index. Always when you sum over a new an
index,
it had better be one downstairs with one
upstairs. Otherwise, you're writing
something that doesn't make sense. Now,
you can So far, I haven't even told you
what this means. So, whether it makes
sense or not, I'm just telling you now
for future purposes, if you're writing
out some equations like this and you
discover that you're summing over
indices, both of which are upstairs or
both of which are downstairs, you made
some mistake.
Okay. This is the nice form that
Lorentz invariant equations should take.
Summing over indices should always be
one up and one down. But,
you'll understand why in due time.
But, let's see what this means. Let's
see exactly what this means. First of
all, what is eta?
Eta is a matrix.
And it's the matrix
-1
0 0 0 0 -1 0 0 0 0 -1 0 0 0 0 +1.
What does it do
when it multiplies a column? Here's a
column.
So, let's put the column there. Let's
multiply eta by mu by by A.
Eta times A, thought of as a matrix
times a column vector A.
That we just get by writing down
A1 A2 A3 and A4.
And let's see what we get. Forget the
left-hand side here. Just let's look at
the product. It gives us minus A1
in the first entry.
Minus A1
minus A2
minus A3 plus A0.
This should be not.
All right. -1 * A1 plus a bunch of zeros
-1 * A2 a bunch of zeros and so forth.
So, you go
between the covariant form and the
contravariant form by multiplying by
this matrix eta. It's a convenient uh
notational device.
Why do we do it? Yeah.
In your last column, I think that should
be negative 2 upstairs
You're getting confused. Yeah, yeah.
Good. Thank you.
In the equation above it, the A lower mu
the indices on the on it should be
upstairs. You're absolutely right.
And in fact, we could identify this with
A1 A2 A3 and A0.
Where these are lower indices. You're
absolutely right.
I was not consistent.
Thank you.
Okay, why would we want to do this?
We want to do this because it's a useful
trick in forming scalars, invariants,
things which don't change under
coordinate transformation. For example,
supposing I take
A mu
and I multiply it by A mu downstairs.
Again, summed over indices which are
repeated.
What does this mean? This means we can
read it directly off here. It's A1
upstairs times minus A1 upstairs. So,
this is just
A1 squared plus No, minus A1 squared
minus A2 squared
minus A3 squared
plus A4 squared.
Well, this is very much like taking the
X vector
and computing the proper
length or the proper time associated
with the X vector. If we go back to the
X vector here, we remember that the
difference
of the time squared components and the
space squared components are what we
called tau, tau squared. Tau squared was
the difference of these components.
And the main feature of it was that it
didn't change from ref- reference frame
to reference frame. It was invariant.
Well, since the A's
by definition transform exactly the same
way as X's, it follows that
this quantity
does not change under Lorentz
transformation.
Or rotation or any other kind of
transformation of the kind we're dealing
with. This is an invariant or a scalar.
So, just as a notational trick to write
in a compact way
uh A1 squared minus A1 squared minus A2
squared minus A3 squared plus A4
squared, we invent the notation with a
lower index and an upper index, where
the lower index changes the sign of all
three space components and leaves the
time component. I keep writing A4, but I
mean A0.
Uh
So, that's just a trick to keep track of
this minus sign
in multiplying vectors
um
to form Lorentz invariant scalars.
For example, in this language, we would
just write
that the proper length of a vector X is
X mu
X mu. And this would stand for T squared
minus X squared minus Y squared minus Z
squared.
Okay. So, that's the notational trick to
keep track of minus signs. And this eta
matrix here is part of that notational
trick. It's just another compact way of
writing that the thing with the lower
components is the thing with the upper
components with the appropriate sign
changes made. Yeah.
That might be like it was a column
vector times a row vector, but we're
looking at this more as just a single
product, so you don't worry about
with the upper mu first.
Uh
Say it again. Oh, well. It looks like
column vector times row vector instead
of row vector times column vector. No, I
mean no.
Uh
I always think of this as column.
This is matrix.
And this is also column.
So, the lower mu is also a column. It's
also a column. Yeah, they're both
labeled. Both should be thought of as
columns. Yeah. This is not going from
columns to rows. The the
Well, in some sense, you can think of it
that way, but I wouldn't, not now. Just
think of them as rows.
Uh sorry, as columns.
Another way to write
A
mu A mu, which is the invariant,
is to write
eta mu nu
A mu A nu.
Why is that? Because if I multiply eta
mu nu by A mu,
well, let's let's change to nu nu nu.
When you sum over an index, it doesn't
matter what you call it.
All right.
So, this lowered the index of A and then
multiplied it by
the uh the contravariant
A.
All right. So, we have various ways to
write the same thing.
No, the order doesn't matter. No.
The order doesn't matter.
Hm?
It's diagonal. First of all, it's
uh it's symmetric.
Yeah. Uh the order doesn't matter. Even
if it wasn't symmetric, it would the
order wouldn't matter.
No, the order does not matter.
Huh. Not until we start doing quantum
mechanics, anyway,
which we're not going to do.
Okay.
Let me prove something else.
Suppose you have two four vectors.
Let's call them A and B.
A mu B mu
is of course exactly the same thing
incidentally
as A sub mu
B super mu. Why is that? Well, both of
them are just
A naught B naught
- A1 B1 - A2 B2
- the same thing for three.
It doesn't matter if you put the upper
index on on A and the lower index on B
or swap them. Lower index on mu on A,
upper index on B. Same thing. You get
the same thing. So, basically the
product we could just think of this as a
new kind of product of A * B
for two four-vectors.
It's not the product of two numbers,
it's the product of two four-vectors.
And the product of two four-vectors
uh the only thing new about it is that
this eta is in there. This funny sign
business. Otherwise, it would be very
much like the dot product of ordinary
vectors.
Now,
what about this object here? Is this
object invariant when you have two
different vectors? If you just have one
vector A and it transforms under Lorentz
transformations,
then this particular combination doesn't
change as you go from frame to frame.
What about if you have two vectors? A *
B.
That also is invariant.
A simple way to prove it.
If A is a four-vector and B is a
four-vector, then A + B and A - B are
both four-vectors.
That means that
A + B
* A + B
These are both four-vectors. A A A and B
are four-vectors. A + B is a
four-vector.
And now when I write product, I mean
product in this sense. One upper and one
lower, but it doesn't matter which one
is upper and which one is lower.
This must be invariant because if A and
B are four-vectors, so is A + B. So,
this is invariant.
What about the difference?
A - B
* A - B
That's also invariant because if you
have two four-vectors, the difference
between them is another four-vector.
Well, this is A squared This is A * A +
B * B
+ 2 * A * B. This is A * A + B * B - 2 *
A * B.
If both of these are invariant, then it
had better be that A * B is also
invariant. Why? Because if you subtract
these If you subtract these, the A
squareds would cancel, the B squareds
would cancel, and you'd just get 2 * A *
B.
2 * A * B is also invariant. So,
anything with one upper index like this
and one lower index,
combine them together, you form an
invariant quantity, which is the same in
every reference frame.
Now, of course, it's good to find things
which are the same in every reference
frame because a
law of nature is supposed to be the same
in every reference frame.
Or a measurement. A measurement of a you
know, distinct quantity should be the
same in every frame. Temperature,
distance between particles, whatever.
All right. Let's Let's go on to consider
some
specific four-vector.
The velocity four-vector, which we did
last time.
But now armed with some powerful
notation,
let's
define some things.
If we have a world line of a particle
and we have two neighboring points,
then the separation between them is a
little infinitesimally small
four-vector. And we can write it as dx
mu.
All right. It has What is it? Let's just
write what its components are. Its
components are dx, dy, dz, and dt.
Or equivalently dx1, dx2, dx3, and dx0.
That's a component That's a four-vector.
All right. It's infinitesimally small.
If we divide that by d tau, and let's
let's work out what d tau is.
D tau
squared
The square of d tau is dt squared - dx
squared - dy squared - dz squared. But
that's just
dx mu dx mu.
Dt squared - dx squared - dy squared dz
- dz squared is d tau is d tau squared.
Or d tau is just the square root of
this.
The dx mu
divided by d tau
Okay. So, this is the rate of change
of the x
of the x coordinate of the x mu
coordinate of the particle, but not rate
of change with ordinary time, but rate
of change
with proper time.
The rate at which the coordinates of the
particle are changing, but as measured
by a clock moving with the particle.
That's the dx mu d tau, and that is
called the proper four-velocity.
U mu.
What are its components? Well, let's we
can
Before I talk about the components of
it,
yeah, this is the four-velocity.
Notice it has four components. That's
weird.
You would think that if you know the
three components of velocity, that you
know everything about how the particle
is moving. And that's true.
The reason is because the fourth
component of the velocity is determined
in terms of the first three components.
Why is that? That's because this
velocity here satisfies a constraint.
Satisfies an relationship, which allows
you to compute the fourth component from
the first three. Let's see what that
constraint is.
I maintain that this object here is a
unit vector.
What does a unit vector mean for a
four-vector? It means that its inner
product with itself or that U mu
U mu
is equal to one.
It's kind of like a a unit vector in
ordinary space.
If you have a unit vector in ordinary
space and you know its x component, then
you also know its y component up to a
sign. There's an ambiguous sign.
All right. Why? Because the sums of the
squares of the components must equal
one. Well, the four-velocity is a unit
vector. How do we see that? Let's just
check that.
Let's just check that. All we have to do
is work it out. Dx mu This is equal to
dx mu by d tau.
Dx mu by d tau.
Upper component, lower component. But
look here. D tau squared is just the dx
mu dx mu. That's what we have in the
numerator. So, the numerator and the
denominator are the same thing. The dx
mu dx mu is d tau squared. In the
denominator, you also have d tau
squared. And so, the four-velocity
is a kind of unit four-vectors.
The four components of the four-velocity
are not independent.
The fourth component, apart from an
ambiguous sign, is completely determined
in terms of the other three components.
If speed is much less If speed is much
less than c, does the four-velocity
become similar to regular velocity? Yes,
let's do that right now.
We did it last time, but I'll remind
you.
That was exactly what I was about to do.
So, let's do it.
Let's do U1, U2, and U3. All right. Just
the x and y and z components.
Let's just call it Ux.
When I'm thinking about space, for some
reason I rather think about x, y, and z
than 1, 2, and 3. But let's let's say U
sub x or U super x is equal to dx by d
tau.
But that's the same as dx by dt * dt by
d tau.
So, we need to know What is this? Of
course, this is just ordinary velocity.
Okay. We can do the same thing for the y
component. This is equal to dy by dt.
Dt by d tau.
Same thing for Uz.
Is equal to dz by dt.
Dt by d tau.
So, for the space components here, we
can just write a simple equation. We can
write one equation. We can write that
U, thought of as a ordinary
three-dimensional vector, is equal to
ordinary velocity.
Let's just call this ordinary velocity
* dt by d tau. That's That's true for
all three components. right? We'll worry
about the fourth component in a minute.
We'll come to the fourth component of
you in a minute, but let's just take the
first three components.
The relation between the ordinary
velocity and the proper velocity is a
simple factor dt by d tau.
Let's work out what that is. Let's work
out what dt by d tau is.
d tau
is equal Now, I'm going to write it out
explicitly. dt squared minus dx squared
minus dy squared minus dz squared.
d tau squared. Sorry, that's d tau
squared, so it's the square root of
this.
Let's Let's leave it this way. d tau
squared.
Now, what we want is dt by d tau.
The ratio of dt and d tau. Let me divide
this
by dt squared.
dt squared
Well, this is easy. This is just 1
minus v squared. This is equal to 1
minus the velocity squared.
The velocity of the particle. Now, we're
not talking about velocities of two
frames of reference necessarily. We're
really just talking about the velocity
of a particle, and to indicate that it's
a three a three-dimensional velocity,
ordinary velocity, I'll put a little
arrow on top of it to indicate ordinary
vector.
1 minus velocity squared is dt by d tau
squared.
Sorry, d tau by dt.
So, all I have to do in order to compute
dt by d tau
is turn it upside down and take its
square root.
So, dt by d tau
That's equal to 1 divided by the square
root of 1 minus v squared.
That's what we called gamma up there.
It's just gamma of v.
It's the same gamma,
but now it's associated with the
velocity of a particle. And it's the
full velocity, all three components of
it squared.
All right. So, now we know the
relationship
between
the four velocities or the first These
are the three components of space of the
four velocity and the ordinary velocity.
Let's just write down what it is.
There's a Oh,
there's a 1 divided by square root of 1
minus v squared, and let's put in c
squared now.
c squared will go over here.
Question.
Yeah, that
that second part there of the dx
dz dx squared dt squared dt by This is
not second derivative. This is the
square of the first derivative.
And because when I do velocity squared,
I get all sorts of cross terms. You do
velocity squared. All right.
Now, v No, no, no, no, no, no. No, no.
Wait.
dx dt plus dy dt plus Oh,
what are we doing? What are we doing? We
calculated No, no.
No, no. Let's do it again.
This is definition.
d tau squared. Definition of d tau
squared is
dt squared minus dx squared minus dy
squared minus dz squared.
That's definition of d tau squared.
Okay. Now, we're just dividing it, and
it's a square of something. It's not the
second derivative of anything. It's just
a square of d tau squared. We divide
that by dt squared.
dt squared by dt squared is just 1.
dx squared by dt squared is is the x
component of velocity squared.
So, this is
minus vx squared.
Well,
that was definition. I actually I didn't
even Yes, but I didn't even really use
it. I just used the definition of what I
meant by d tau squared, but it just was,
as you said, the uh the dot product
squared. Yeah.
Yeah.
Okay. So, there we are. We have
This is the space components of the four
velocity, and all you do is multiply the
ordinary velocity which with by a number
which is very, very close to 1
if the velocity is much smaller than c.
So,
I'm a little confused at this point.
Mhm.
Um
because I was not thinking of
that v
as the relative velocity between two
coordinate frames. It's not now. It's
just the velocity of a particle in some
particular frame. So,
it kind of looks
It's the same It's a It's a similar
mathematical expression,
but yeah.
Yeah, you could I tried to steer you out
of that by saying it's not the velocity
of another frame. Yeah. Right. Right,
but No, let's let's Okay, let's say it
even again. I I Right.
This gamma of v here
is a particular function of the
magnitude of a velocity, any velocity.
If it happens to be the velocity of a
particle,
it's velocity of a particle. If it's the
velocity of a moving frame, it's the
velocity of a moving frame, but its
definition is
1 divided by the square root of 1 minus
v squared.
That's its definition, where v squared
here means the square of the magnitude
of the velocity, ordinary velocity
squared. The same velocity that if you
were to write the kinetic energy, it
would be 1/2 mv squared, same velocity
squared here.
Okay. So, if it's a particle,
we put in its velocity, all three
components, we sum them and square them,
and that defines this quantity here.
It also happens to be the same
mathematical expression that goes into
the Lorentz transformation.
That
It's not completely accidental, but at
this point it's just
a notation for a particular function.
Okay. So, this is This is the first
three components of you. What about the
fourth component of you?
The fourth component of you is by
definition dt by d tau.
Well, it's dx not
by d tau,
which is the same as dt by d tau.
And that is just 1 divided
by square root of 1 minus v squared over
c squared.
That's what dt d tau was.
All right. So, we now know what the four
components of you are in terms of the
ordinary velocities.
Okay.
First of all,
they're bigger than the ordinary
velocities. 1 minus v squared over c
squared is always less than 1. 1 over it
is greater than 1, and so forth.
So, the space components of the velocity
are always bigger
than the uh component of ordinary
velocity. Notice something very strange
happens when the velocity gets to be up
near the speed of light, ordinary
velocity. When ordinary velocity
approaches the speed of light, you grows
enormous.
So,
four velocity gets hugely big
when the when the ordinary
three-dimensional velocity gets near the
speed of light.
What about the fourth component?
The fourth component, if the velocity is
small, is essentially 1.
The fourth component is just the number
in the limit that the velocity is small.
When the velocity gets big or gets up
near the speed of light, then u naught
also gets big.
Doesn't u naught need the units of
velocity?
What's that? Doesn't u naught need the
units of velocity?
Well, don't forget the set the speed of
light equal to 1. So,
uh so, we've lost that particular fact.
Um we could multiply it by velocity, the
speed of light, and give it give it
components of the velocity.
If we wanted it to have Sorry, if we
wanted it to have units of velocity when
the speed of light was not equal to 1,
we would multiply it by c.
Uh and that's fine. You can do that if
you like.
Um it does You just have to remember
what you're talking about. It's more
usual to think of the fourth component
of the velocity as something near 1.
Uh but you can think of it as being near
c.
Now, that brings us to the four
components of momentum.
Let's talk about a particle. Let it be a
particle, any object that has a certain
rest mass. We call the rest mass m.
Then, it has
four components. It's also a four
vector.
Momentum is Standard notation for it is
to call it P.
That's true in
Newtonian mechanics, it's true in
relativistic mechanics, momentum the
symbol is P. Now, in non-relativistic
physics is just m * v.
Mass times velocity, but that's not a
very good four-vector. Mass times
ordinary velocity, it's not a
four-vector.
If we want to make a four-vector out of
it because we're going to want to write
equations which make sense in every
reference frame,
then we want to take it to be mass
times U mu.
Right?
That's, of course, mass
times V mu
divided by square root of 1 minus V
squared over C squared, but I won't
bother writing the C squared now.
So,
that's a definition, if you like. This
is the definition of the momentum of an
object of mass m moving with velocity U,
moving with four velocity U.
And it has four components.
The first three components are very
close
to the ordinary momentum when the
velocity is small.
The last component is the energy.
I showed you that last time, it's
essentially mc squared
plus
1/2 mv squared. Now, I'll come back to
that.
Uh
We'll come
We'll come back to that.
But, um
let's just note that this is the
definition of the four components of
velocity uh momentum.
All right, the law of physics that we're
going to study,
I think we may actually get to it
tonight. In fact, I think we might
actually be there.
About to start it, anyway.
Um
No, V is not a four-vector.
Right.
I did.
It does have four components, though,
one of which is just one.
Uh
Let's just get rid of this side of the
equation. Not Not get ourselves
confused.
Right.
All right, what we're going to do now is
we're going to take a bit of a vacation
from relativity,
and we're going to write the law of
motion the ordinary laws of motion even
before relativity.
They're going.
Noisy little bastards. Excuse me.
P mu is equal to yeah.
All right.
Now, what I want to do is pick a law of
physics, an important law of physics.
Think about it from the point of view
pre-Einstein,
and then try to figure out how we would
um
redesign it, change it, modify it so
that it would become a relativistically
invariant law of motion.
It's the law of motion of
charged particles in electric and
magnetic fields.
Now, I'll tell you right now,
the decomposition into electric and
magnetic is not an invariant
decomposition.
What in one frame of reference is a
magnetic field may become a combination
of electric and magnetic in another
frame, and vice versa.
So,
I want to write down first the non the
the pre-Einstein law of motion of a
particle,
charged particle, in an electromagnetic
field, and then we can try to think, how
do we modify this in order to make it
a legitimate um
relativistic equation that will be the
same in every reference frame. As I
write it, it will not be the same in
every reference frame,
because it will be based
on pre-Einstein physics.
And the fact that it's not the same in
every reference frame is one of the
things that really led Einstein to say,
"Something's wrong with with ordinary uh
kinematics, with ordinary space and time
and motion."
All right.
Here's our law.
First of all, F equals MA.
Force is mass times acceleration. Now,
we haven't even talked about
acceleration,
but
I think we can guess the rule for what
relativistic acceleration is.
If
ordinary acceleration is the time rate
of change of velocity,
then I don't think it would surprise you
very much at this point if I told you
that the four-dimensional acceleration
is
the proper time rate of change
of
the four-dimensional
velocity vector.
Remember that the first three components
of U are very close to the ordinary
velocity,
and tau is very close ordinary time
uh for slowly moving objects.
So, for slowly moving objects, the first
three components are very close to the
acceleration, ordinary acceleration.
But, uh we'll come back to this. For the
time being, let's just think about
ordinary acceleration,
the old-fashioned kind,
F equals MA.
All we need to know in order to write
down Newton's equations for the motion
of a particle is what the force on it
is. The force of an electric particle of
an electrically charged particle, the
force on an electrically charged
particle, is made up out of the electric
field,
which is a three-vector, meaning to say
it has three components, X, Y, and Z.
Something not good about that. And also
the magnetic field,
which also has three components.
Something not good about that, too. I
mean, because after all, we want to
write things in terms of
four-dimensional objects, not in terms
of three-dimensional objects.
So, there's going to be something quite
non in not right about what we're going
to write down, at least until we we
learn to understand better the relation
between electric and magnetic fields.
But, for the time being, let's just
write down
the force law, and here it is. This is
Lorentz's force law, discovered by
Lorentz sometime around, I don't know,
1895.
Of course, it was always known
that it was proportional to the electric
charge.
It was known
that
This is acceleration. Everything is an
ordinary three-dimensional vector here.
There was charge times electric field.
That goes back to who? Where Who was the
first one who wrote down charge times
electric field? Faraday.
Faraday first had the idea of electric
fields. If you put charges into electric
fields,
uh forces are exerted on them.
And then plus
also charge
times the velocity
cross the magnetic field. Okay, now I
have to tell you what the cross product
is.
Anybody Anybody not know what the cross
product is?
Okay.
In a moment, anyway.
This piece of the force
is called velocity independent. There's
no velocity in here. There is a velocity
in here.
Okay?
But, remember, velocity, what in one
frame of reference a particle may have
Let's suppose there was no electric
field altogether.
Okay?
But, because the particle is moving with
a velocity in a magnetic field, there's
a force on it.
Okay?
That's interesting, because in some
other frame of reference,
the velocity may be zero.
If the velocity is zero, then there
would be no contribution to the force
from here, but there's a force on it.
We've just seen there's a force on it.
The force on it makes it accelerated. If
it If it accelerates in one frame, it
accelerates in every frame.
Or another way to say it is if it
doesn't accelerate in one frame, it
doesn't accelerate in another frame.
And so, something's funny here.
If there was only a magnetic field, if
there was only a magnetic field,
then in some other frame of reference,
there would have to be an electric
field.
Okay? In a frame of reference in which
the velocity of the particle was zero, a
frame moving with the particle, that
force could only come from the electric
field. So, that immediately tells us
that electric and magnetic fields have
to mix up with each other when you do
Lorentz transformations.
Right? What is the connection between
electric and magnetic fields? And the
connection is that the two of them
together form a new kind of object which
we haven't we haven't written down yet.
It's called a tensor. Here's an object
which has six components all together.
It's surely not a scalar. It's got
components X, Y, and Z. B also has
components X, Y, and Z.
Uh it doesn't have four components. It
has six components all together, so it's
not a four-vector. It's something new.
Right? It's got to be something new and
moreover, it should these things
transform into each other under various
kinds of Lorentz transformations. That's
what we know.
So, the next question is what kind of
other objects are there that we can
define
besides scalars and vectors? And the
next class of objects is called tensors.
In order to write down what the
electromagnetic field is from the point
of view of relativity, we have to
understand tensors.
Tensors are the new ingredient.
Well, let me tell you first of all, the
simplest way to think about a tensor.
I'm going to call tensors T.
Capital T.
A scalar is a tensor.
It's called a tensor of zero rank. It
has no indices. Why does it have no
indices? Because a scalar has no
indices. A scalar doesn't have any
components. So, a scalar is the simplest
kind of tensor.
A vector,
a four-vector, a four-vector is also a
tensor.
Okay? But, it's a tensor of rank one,
which means it's an object which has
only Well, let's call it A.
A
mu. It has only one index. It has four
components,
but it has only one index. That index
can run over four different values.
A tensor is a thing which has two
indices. The simplest tensor is to take
two vectors. Let's call them A and B,
and B does not stand for the magnetic
field now.
Okay? Maybe I should call it C. I'll
call it B.
All right. Take another four-vector and
put them next to each other.
There's an object. It's an object which
has how many components all together?
It's got 16 components all together,
right? 16 components because A has four
components, B has four components.
Mu and nu each can be anything from one
to four or from zero to three. And so,
all together there are 16 components. We
could display these 16 components as a
matrix as a 4 by 4 matrix.
In the first place, we would put A zero
let's say A1 B1. Then, I think it's A1
B2. A1 B3.
A1 B0. And then A2 B1 and so forth. We
could display them
all four compo all 16 components,
just lay them out on a grid and draw a
matrix for them.
That's the simplest form of tensor. Just
take two vectors
and juxtapose them together. Take all 16
components.
And those 16 components form an object
which is called a second rank tensor.
You could take three vectors. Take a
third vector.
Now, we would have to make a cube to
represent it.
Let's take a
Uh first of all, this is a second rank
vector. Sorry, second rank tensor.
Don't worry about why it's called a
tensor. I mean, is it nervous?
Uh
it's not nervous. It's not the it's
Actually, it does come from the word
tense, but not the
It's not nervous. It just has two
indices. All right. Second rank tensor.
Of course, we can construct third rank
tensors.
A third rank tensor would be made out of
three vectors.
Mu, nu,
sigma, let's say.
Okay?
That would be a third rank tensor. How
many components does it have? 4 * 4 =
16. 64 components. And if we wanted to
display them, we might display them on a
as cells in a cube.
And thus it goes. We could have fourth
rank tensors, fifth rank tensors. Now,
what is it that characterizes a tensor?
Is it just a product of two vectors? No.
It's any object which transforms the
same way as a product of two vectors.
Right? So, let's let's ask how a product
of two vectors transforms. The product
all 16 components.
Supposing we know
the components of A,
then the components of A prime in
another frame of reference are by
definition L mu nu
A nu.
That's the transformation property of A.
It's also the transformation property of
B.
B prime mu mu.
Let's use a different variable, sigma.
Is equal to L sigma tau
A
tau.
All right. Remember,
it doesn't matter what you call the
summation index. I call this one nu and
I call this one tau, but on the
left-hand side I have an open sigma
index, which means this really does
correspond to some particular component
and we have a sigma on this side.
All right. What How does What's the
transformation property of A
prime mu
B prime sigma?
That's the primed
component, the mu sigma component of the
prime tensor. Prime means that's
components in the primed reference
frame. Well, it's very easy.
Just L
mu nu
L
Yes.
A nu
B tau.
All right. So, whatever a tensor is,
it transforms with an object which has
two L's in it.
One for each index.
Here's the mu index.
Here's the sigma index.
Notice that the lower component of this
L goes with A. The upper component of
this L also goes with A prime. The lower
component
tau goes with B. The upper component
sigma also goes with B. B prime in this
case. Now, I can tell you what the
general law of a second rank tensor
transformation is. The general law is
take
a tensor
in the primed reference frame
is given by exactly the same kind of
structure L mu nu
L sigma tau
T
nu
tau.
Okay? So, here's the rule.
If you know the components of T in one
frame, the unprimed frame, then you take
the L's, the Lorentz transformation
matrices, and you simply apply them.
The nu index transforms into the mu
index
by the mu nu matrix. The sigma index the
tau index becomes the sigma index
by L sigma tau.
Okay. So, you see the pattern. This
pattern repeats itself. If there's a
third rank tensor, then there's just one
more L,
making it transform just as if it were
the product of three vectors.
This is what is called a tensor.
You can't ask me why that's called a
tensor, and you can't ask me why I wrote
it down. All you can say is it useful?
Is it useful to define it? It is very
useful to define it. But, here's its
definition. It's a thing which
transforms as if it were the 16
components of the product of two
vectors. Now, there are other things. It
doesn't have to be the product of two
vectors. For example, here's something.
Take A mu
B sigma. That's not the same not the
same as A sigma B mu.
It's not the same thing. If, for
example, I take the 1 3 matrix element,
the 1 3 matrix element of this will be
A1 B3.
The 1 3 matrix element of this, or the 1
3 component of this, will be
A3
B1. So, they're not the same thing.
A mu B sigma and A sigma B mu.
But, both of them transform as tensors.
You could add them.
The result is still a tensor, but it is
not an object which is just a product of
two vectors. You could do other things.
You could have take some third vector,
and you could add some third and fourth
vector, and add it, C mu D sigma.
C mu D sigma is a tensor.
If you add it to some previous tensor,
it is still a tensor. It still
transforms the same way.
So, not every tensor is just a product
of two vectors, but every tensor
transforms the same way as a product of
two tensors two vectors.
Now, there are two special kinds of
tensors of rank two.
Rank two.
All right?
The two special kinds are called
anti-symmetric and symmetric.
An anti-symmetric tensor is one that has
the property
T mu nu
equals T nu mu. This is symmetric,
sorry.
That's symmetric.
That says that T12 equals T21.
Symmetric, it doesn't In this case, it
doesn't matter
which order you put the indices. That's
called a symmetric tensor of rank two.
An anti-symmetric tensor of rank two
is one which changes sign when you
change
when you flip it.
In terms of matrices,
they correspond to the symmetric and
anti-symmetric matrices.
So, if we take
a
symmetric tensor,
and we display its all 16 components of
it,
then it will have the property
that it will be symmetric. The 1 2
element over here
will be the same as the T the 2 1
element over here.
The 1 1 element will be whatever it is.
The 2 2 element will be whatever it is.
But, then T13
will equal T31.
T13 will be the same. So, the matrix
will have a symmetry. It'll be a
symmetric matrix, which means that the
components off the diagonal
will reflect into each other. That's a
symmetric matrix. But, more interesting
for us
today and the next time is going to be
the anti-symmetric matrix.
What about the anti-symmetric matrix?
That has the property, when you reflect
it, it changes sign.
T13 is minus T31.
What about T11?
It's got to be minus T11.
All right? T11 must be minus T11. Well,
if T11 is minus T11,
then the anti-symmetric matrix
must have zeros on the diagonal.
Zeros on the diagonal.
Let's
And then off diagonal, it has T12,
T13,
T10.
Let's let's do it nicely.
I'm going to make a nice big matrix,
and I'm going to subdivide it into four,
and then put its components. This is an
anti-symmetric tensor.
Its diagonal elements all have to be
zero.
That's because T11 must equal minus T11.
On the other hand, T12
has to equal minus
T21.
So, T12 up here and minus T12 over here.
This is minus this.
T13
minus T13.
And finally, T10
minus T10.
What about over here? Here we have
T21.
And over here, it must be minus T21.
Here's T
20.
This is minus T20.
And finally, down here, what do we have?
T uh
T30
minus T30.
So, it's anti-symmetric, which means
that when you reflect it about the
diagonal, it changes sign.
An anti-symmetric also means that it
changes sign when you interchange the
two indices.
Those are called symmetric and
anti-symmetric tensors.
How many
How many interesting components
does a symmetric tensor have? Let's
count them. A symmetric tensor
has four diagonal components,
1 2 3 4.
And then how many off diagonal
components? Let's uh let's
There are of course 16 components all
together.
But,
the component over here is not
independent of the component over here.
So, really the independent components,
the number of numbers that you need to
know, is 1 2 3 4
5 6 7 8 9. Nine? No.
10.
1 2 3 4 5 6
7 8 9 10.
10 independent components
determine a symmetric tensor.
Okay.
So, what? So, nothing.
But, how many an anti-symmetric tensor?
Well, for an anti-symmetric tensor,
there are zeros on the diagonal.
So, we can subtract four of them.
Only this this this
this this and this.
Zeros on the diagonal.
And the other ones off on the other half
of the matrix here are determined in
terms of these. How many is that? Six.
Six.
That's the number of components of the
electric and magnetic field.
Okay.
That's the number of components of
electric and magnetic fields.
This is the only object that you can
construct, the anti-symmetric tensor
is in fact the only object that has six
components and which transforms Well,
you could take six scalars. Six scalars
or a four vector and two scalars would
would also have six components.
But, none of those are correspond to the
electric and magnetic field.
The electric and magnetic field form an
anti-symmetric tensor.
They form an anti-symmetric tensor,
and out of that anti-symmetric tensor,
we want to understand this equation
here,
and how it transforms under Lorentz
transformation.
Now,
it does transform in a complicated way.
And that means that the electric and
magnetic fields are going to transform
into each other. I'm going to write down
We're going to finish now. I'm going to
I'm going to write down for next time
I'm going to write down the precise
relationship, but we're going to derive
this.
We're going to derive this, but I'm
going to write now write down the
precise relationship between the
anti-symmetric tensor and the components
of the electric and magnetic field.
How do the components of the electric
and magnetic field
combine themselves together to make an
anti-symmetric tensor?
So,
we take our
4 by 4 matrix.
Which I'll draw some guidelines so that
I know where the elements are.
Zeros on the diagonal.
The off diagonal, I don't need to
specify both above and below. Once I
specify above, you can read off what's
below just by changing the sign.
And here I'm going to tell you what they
are.
Mhm. This is
uh 1 2 3 0 1 2 3 0. X Y Z T.
This is the 1 2 component.
In the 1 2 component, we put
minus
the third component of the magnetic
field, Bz.
Let's see. Did I
We put the third component in that In
the 1 2 place, we put the third
component of the magnetic field. In the
1 3 place,
we put the second component of the
magnetic field, the Y component of the
magnetic field.
And you guess what goes down here? Down
here goes minus
the first component of the magnetic
field.
Right? So, if we didn't have time,
suppose we didn't have time, we only had
one, two, and three,
then the anti-symmetric tensor would
only have three components.
And those three components would be
identified
with the three components of the
magnetic field.
We're going to discuss this further, but
for the for the time being,
this is the setup for the way that the
magnetic field enters into a
anti-symmetric tensor. Now, Are they all
minuses?
No.
Minus, plus, minus. We'll see why.
Are those supposed to be thought of as
coordinates
Yeah. This could be This could be the Z
component.
This could be the Y component, or would
be. This could be the X component.
And then we would write XYZ time. Okay?
Is that what you meant? Yes. Yeah, okay.
All right. Now, we have three entries
over here, three more entries.
Obviously, those three entries must have
something to do with the electric field,
and of course they do.
EX, EY,
EZ.
Do I have the sign right? Yeah.
Let's just put in what goes down here
just to fill it out. We have plus BZ
here,
minus BY here,
minus EX here,
plus BX here,
uh let's see.
Minus EY,
and minus EZ.
So, it's now got six independent
components,
and it fills out a 4x4 matrix,
anti-symmetric 4x4 matrix,
with electric fields in the time
slot here, and magnetic fields in the
space-space slots. The space-space
components are magnetic fields, the
space-time components are electric
fields.
Now, why is this? How did I know this?
How did anybody know it?
We'll come to that next time.
What They know it by fiddling around and
trying to find a sensible
uh relativistic generalization of this
formula here.
So, the next time we'll work that out.
We'll work out F equals MA for a
particle in an electric and magnetic
field, except in relativistic notation.
Incidentally,
this 4x4 matrix here is not usually
called T mu nu, it's called F mu nu.
I don't know the history of what F why F
is called F,
but I suspect it's Faraday.
I suspect F
stood for the Faraday tensor.
Uh
and it's anti-symmetric,
and it's composed of the magnetic and
electric fields.
So, each of those numbers is the
strength of the field
in the XY It's the components of the
field.
The components of the field.
Yeah.
So,
Yeah, let's let's just concentrate on
the magnetic part of it here.
Let's uh
Let's put a little fence around
the time stuff and get rid of it for a
moment.
All right.
This now just constitutes a
three-dimensional tensor, anti-symmetric
tensor.
And let's write down equation.
This equation says that
F12
is equal to minus BZ,
or minus B3.
Three is there Three is Z.
Next,
F13
is equal to plus BY.
And finally, F
What's the last one down here? The last
one is two, three. F23
is equal to B
X.
In fact,
three This is three. Minus B X. Yes,
minus. Minus B1
B2.
Okay. Now, I can write this in a nicer
form, a nicer form where you'll see the
pattern.
Let's write this one not as F13,
but rather as minus F31.
If I write this as minus F31,
then I have that F31
is B2, and F23 is minus B1.
All right. What What do I see in that
form that I like about it?
Let me show you how it works.
Let's Let's start with the equation F12
equals minus B3.
And let's cycle from one to two to three
in each spot.
In each spot, the next equation will go
one to two,
two to three, three to one. Make a
clock.
A clock that goes around in a circle,
one, two, three, and let's proceed
clockwise.
All right. The next equation down,
everything would cycle forward. So, what
would happen to the one?
Become two.
What would happen to the two?
Three.
What would happen to the three?
Minus B1.
What's the next one? One, two, the next
one would be three. F3
two, three,
one
equals minus
three, one, two.
Well, with any luck at all, that will be
exactly what we wrote here. Let's see.
F12 is minus B3.
F31 is minus B2. Don't worry about
whether they're upstairs or downstairs.
Forget that.
F23 is minus B1.
So,
this has a very nice
structure to it.
The one, two component of the tensor is
the third component of the magnetic
field. The two, three component of the
tensor
is the one component, and it cycles.
One, two, three
two, three, one three, one, two.
So, you can always remember All you have
to remember is one of them, and the
others will follow just by cycling
the uh the numbers from one to two to
three. Now, the electric field is
different. The electric fields
E1
is equal to F10.
E2 is F20,
and E3 is F30.
So, the electric fields
are vectors where you just ignore the
time component here.
And you see what the index structure is.
E1 is F10, E2 is F20, E3 is F30. The
magnetic field, a little more
complicated.
There's something you might notice. The
magnetic field seems to have two
identities.
It has an identity as an anti-symmetric
tensor whose components are called F,
and it has another identity
as a kind of vector, ordinary
three-dimensional vectors. When I speak
of vectors now, I'm speaking of
three-dimensional vectors.
It has an identity as an anti-symmetric
tensor
in three dimensions,
minus B, B, B,
minus sign here, and it has a second
identity as a vector.
That connection between anti-symmetric
tensors and vectors is only true in
three dimensions. It is not something
which is true in other dimensions. It's
just an accident.
Well, it's not exactly an accident,
but think of it as roughly accidental,
that if you take a 3x3 anti-symmetric
matrix, it happens to have three
independent components. Those three
independent components also happen to
form
an ordinary three-dimensional vector.
But if you have a 4x4 matrix,
anti-symmetric, it cannot be identified
with a four vector. So,
we see that the magnetic field sort of
has two identities. In one identity, it
has two indices, and the other identity,
it has only one index.
Uh
We're going to build, next time, out of
this anti-symmetric tensor,
and four velocities and four
accelerations, four-dimensional
accelerations, we're going to build an
equation which we'll recognize as having
transformation properties that make
certain that it's the same in every
reference frame. That's our goal, to
rewrite this so that it's the same in
every reference frame. We'll have to
modify it a bit. This is not quite right
as it is.
And when we modify it, it will form an
equation which is the same in every
reference frame. Yeah.
So, was Einstein
looking for this um the Lorentz
invariant formulation of
electromagnetism on the conceptual
grounds or did he have any empirical
Could you say it again?
Was he doing that just on conceptual
grounds? Yeah.
Yeah. He He had a suspicion that the
laws of nature ought to be the same in
every reference frame.
Um
this was a matter of intuition to him or
matter of conviction. And of course
also had a good deal of experimental
support, the fact that the speed of
light was the same in every reference
frame as far as we measured that nobody
could detect
using light the motion of the earth
through through through space.
But uh
um
I don't even think he knew that. I don't
know I don't know if he knew it. He said
he didn't know it. I don't know if he
knew it or not.
Um
but uh he he
himself, according to his own
description,
was more influenced by
the principle of relativity
and he could not make
these equations be the same in every
reference frame, not without doing
something to mix E and B up and even
that wasn't enough.
He had to mix up the components of the
velocity. Eventually he had to figure
out special relativity.
He did not actually write the his
equations in four-vector notation.
Uh
he just
put in all the various extra gammas and
functions of velocity. But what he was
doing was basically making sure that the
equations were the same in every
reference frame by making them into
four-vector equations.
It was Minkowski who really put together
the four-vector idea
and rewrote the equations in a
four-vector notation.
But um
Einstein was more or less clumsily
somewhat clumsy clumsily uh going about
writing these equations in a way that
they would go from one frame to a next
by some systematic transformation
properties and they would always be the
same in all reference frames.
So, yeah. It was It was essentially a
conceptual guess on his part
that Maxwell's equations, together with
the Lorentz force law, should be the
same in every reference frame.
So, he developed Lorentz tensors for
general relativity. Did he feel silly
about special relativity then?
No.
At first he I I I don't know a hell of a
lot about the history of it. And you
know,
history is always in the eye of the
beholder and what the people say is not
always exactly what was what happened.
So, I I don't really know, but
I think according to his own writings,
he at first did not like Minkowski's
ideas. He didn't like the idea of
four-dimensional geometry at first.
Uh
it didn't take him long to catch on, but
at first
he simply wrote everything out in in
sort of clumsy brutal form
and uh
had a hard time adjusting to the neater
notation.
That's what he said anyway.
Did Minkowski come up with this in about
a year or so after I think it was 2
years. It was 1907 if I remember. You
know,
yeah. Well, in two things move slower at
that time than they do now.
That's pretty fast. Yeah.
Yeah.
Well, I think if it was today it would
have happened much faster, but So,
was Minkowski a mathematician or
physicist? Well, I'm not sure that
people necessarily distinguish that at
time. Um
and I don't know I don't know that he
was that
that he contributed much else to
physics. Not that not that this wasn't
enough. I mean, this was a huge amount
to contribute. But I don't know what
else he did. I mean,
there's there was no long history of
famous papers by Minkowski.
Uh
this was essentially his um
high point.
No.
Hm?
We don't know.
Was he affected by
Lorentz? Don't know.
I think probably yes.
Was he affected by Fitzgerald? Who
knows?
I don't know.
One thing I know is you don't trust
people when when they give answers to
those questions. They don't remember.
So, do you know if
if the tensor transformation of E and B
was in his first paper in 1907?
No, no.
It was in Einstein's paper in 1905.
1905? Yeah. But he just had it, you
know, um
you know, written out by hand. You know,
you know, when Maxwell wrote his
equations, he wrote every single
equation, the X component, the Y
component, the Z component. How many of
them are all there altogether?
Let's see. There's E dot, there's one
equation.
E dot, that's three equations. Six
equations.
Seven eight equa- eight equations?
I think eight equations altogether.
No, no, no, no. It's more than that. But
I don't
Sorry.
I don't know.
So, this was three six
eight equations.
And I think he wrote out all the X
component of this uh X component of
this. 1 2 3 4 5 6.
Yeah, he wrote down all eight equations
and never put them together into some
nice uh symbolic form. Well, Einstein
was doing essential the exactly the same
thing in space-time. He was just writing
everything out
uh and uh sort of doing it by trial and
error. You get the feeling when you read
the paper that he did it by trial and
error rather than anything as systematic
as four-vectors. It was Minkowski who
understood the the four-vector idea.
So, uh
uh this is some hit and miss for
Einstein
with some good intuition about uh
Okay, let's uh next time we'll come back
and we will work out
the Lorentz force law as modified by
Einstein and Minkowski.
The preceding program is copyrighted by
Stanford University. Please visit us at
stanford.edu.